Sidney R. Anderson Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Sidney R. Anderson Papers
1914-2005
1955-1978
RG 200
Yale University Divinity School Library
6
(12 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, photographs, slides, and collected material document the life and work of Sidney and Olive Anderson, who were Methodist missionaries in China and Hong Kong from 1915 to 1963. They were instrumental in the development of the Moore Memorial Church in Shanghai and spent twelve years in Hong Kong after 1951 working with refugees from mainland China and at the North Point Methodist Church.
Anderson, Sidney Raymond, 1889-1978
Anderson, Olive, 1890-1978
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Sidney R. Anderson, Jr., 2006-2008
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
Chronology of Sidney Anderson
1889 Dec 7 Sidney Raymond Anderson born in Rising Star, Texas
1911 Graduated from Polytechnic College (later Southern Methodist University)
1914 Graduated from Vanderbilt Divinity School
1914 Went to China under the Board of Missions, Methodist Episcopal Church, South
1915 Ordained at the East China Conference, Soochow; worked in cities and villages in Kiangsu and Chekiang
1920 Returned to U.S. on furlough, married Olive Lipscomb (1890-1978), who had also served in China. Studied at Columbia University and Union Seminary in New York. Olive's mother, Bessie Lipscomb was a Secretary in the Board of Missions and lived in Nashville.
1921-1949 Returned to China and worked primarily at Moore Memorial Church in Shanghai. Developed an active program at the church and built a new building. Instrumental in developing conferences for young people, adult education programs, and village welfare schools.
1922 Sidney R. Anderson, Jr. born in Shanghai
1951-1963 Following a furlough in the U.S. began work in Hong Kong primarily among refugees from mainland China and at North Point Methodist Church.
1964 Retired to San Francisco and worked among the Chinese there.
1971 Moved to the Wesley Woods Retirement Center in Atlanta, Georgia
1978 Sidney and Olive Anderson died.
Scope and Contents
The Sidney R. Anderson Papers consist of correspondence, writings, photographs, slides, printed material, and personal papers documenting the life and work of Methodist missionaries Sidney and Olive Anderson. The collection spans the years 1914 to 2005, with the bulk of the collection dating from the 1950s to the 1970s. Correspondence and printed material document the Andersons' work at Moore Memorial Church in Shanghai, but the majority of the collection relates to their work in Hong Kong and with Chinese students and acquaintances whom they assisted in various ways, particularly the Luk family. Biographical information and a book written by the Andersons' son, Sidney R. Anderson, Jr., provide context for documentation of their work.
The Addendum of Series VIII contains material that was received after the bulk of the collection had already been processed. It includes the majority of the documentation of their years of service in China.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1955-1978
II. Writings, 1945-2005
III. Documentation of Work in Hong Kong, 1951-1967
IV. Collected Material, 1935-1976
V. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1962-1978
VI. Photographs, 1914-1970
VII. Slides, 1955-1969
VIII. Addendum, 1915-1980
Methodist Church -- Missions -- China; Methodist Church -- Missions -- China -- Hong Kong; Missions -- China; Missions -- China -- Hong Kong; Missionaries
- Correspondence, 1955-1978; Series I
  - Personal letters, including from Sidney to his wife, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Personal letters, including mimeographed letter from Andersons providing information about students they had helped, 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal letters, including to/from students helped by the Andersons, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Personal letters, including to/from students helped by the Andersons, 1970-1977,n.d (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Circular letters from missionary colleagues, 1961-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Circular letter from Sid and Olive Anderson, from Moore Memorial Church, Shanghai, 1950 Mar (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Mission-related letters written while Sidney was Hong Kong Treasurer, Division of World Missions, Board of Missions of the Methodist Church, incl. re. missionary personnel, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Mission-related letters written while Sidney was Hong Kong Treasurer, Division of World Missions, Board of Missions of the Methodist Church, incl. re. missionary personnel, 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Mission-related letters, incl. re. mission finance, while Andersons were in San Francisco, 1967- 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
- Writings, 1945-2005; Series II
  - By Sidney R. Anderson
    - Sermons/talks - including "A Brief Glance at Methodist History in China", 1945-1975, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    - Notes and Essays, 1955-1964, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - By Sidney R. Anderson, Jr.
    - China My Great Teacher: Lu Shan, My Shangri La (autobiographical work on growing up as a missionary kid in colonial Hong Kong in the1930s), 2005 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Documentation of Work in Hong Kong, 1951-1967; Series III
  - Materials in Chinese, 1955-1967 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - North Point Methodist Church: Budget, 1953, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - North Point Methodist Church: Correspondence, 1951-1953,n.d (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - North Point Methodist Church: Meeting minutes, agenda, notes, 1952, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - North Point Methodist Church: Members listings, 1952, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Collected Material, 1935-1976; Series IV
  - Re. Mission Work
    - Chung Chi College, 1955-1965,n.d (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Hong Kong, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Methodist Church (Wei Li Kung Hui), including reproductions of paintings of Bishop Arthur James Moore and Martha McDonald Moore, 1953-1971 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Ward Memorial Methodist Church; Methodist Church in Taiwan and U.S., 1964-1976,n.d (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - North Point Methodist Church, 1963-1967 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Soochow University, 1935, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Wesley Village, Hong Kong (for refugees), 1955-1965 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Notes, tribute to Andersons by Mary Ellen Hawk Sanders, 1969-1979, n.d.. (Box 3, Folder 28-29)
    - Various brochures, flyers, pamphlets, 1963,1966, n.d (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - African-Americans, 1969, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - China, 1963-1969,n.d (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Chinatown, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Hong Kong, 1969, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Japan, 1966, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Miscellaneous., 1965-1969, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 36-37)
    - Peking, 1964-1967,n.d (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Scientology, 1969 Aug (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Soviet Union, 1969 Aug, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Vietnam, 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Writings by others
    - "China Log" by Sterling G. Brinkley, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - "Prison Limericks" by F. Olin Stockwell, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - "The Stewardship of the Methodist Church in Hong Kong" by Leo L. Hsu, 1962 May 15 (Box 3, Folder 45)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1962-1978; Series V
  - Financial material, 1963-1970,n.d (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Related to Luk Family
    - Biographical sketch, cards, memorabilia, 1973, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 47-48)
    - Correspondence: Alice and Katherine Luk, 1972-1977,n.d (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Correspondence: David Luk, 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Correspondence: John Luk, 1972-1976 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Correspondence: Miranda Luk, 1968-1976,n.d (Box 4, Folder 52-54)
    - Account information and correspondence: Miranda and Katherine Luk:, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Correspondence Peter Luk, 1972-1978 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Various correspondence re. Luk family, 1968-1978, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 57-58)
    - Immigration documents and materials, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Photographs, 1962-1973 (Box 5, Folder 60)
- Photographs, 1914-1970; Series VI
  - Photo of women students marching with flag, 1930s (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Group of African Americans; portrait of Chinese woman, 1943,1949 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Primarily group and individual portraits of Chinese individuals, incl. worship service at North Point Methodist Church and Christmas pageant, 1950-1953 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Primarily groups and individual portraits of Chinese individuals, incl. at North Point Methodist Church, 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Primarily groups and individual portraits of Chinese individuals, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Bishop Ward's Funeral, 1958 Dec (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Primarily groups and individual portraits of Chinese individuals, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Primarily groups and individual portraits of Chinese individuals, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Primarily groups and individual portraits of Chinese individuals, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Primarily groups and individual portraits of Chinese individuals, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Primarily groups and individual portraits of Chinese individuals, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - Primarily groups and individual portraits of Chinese individuals, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Primarily groups and individual portraits of Chinese individuals, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Primarily groups and individual portraits of Chinese individuals, 1965-1966 (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Primarily groups and individual portraits of Chinese individuals, 1967,1969 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Primarily groups and individual portraits of Chinese individuals, 1970's (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Primarily groups and individual portraits of Chinese individuals (Box 6, Folder 77-82)
  - Portraits of Sidney and Olive Anderson, 1969-1970s, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - Portraits and scenery, 1957-1962, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 83-88)
  - Oversized photographs, 1914-1920 (Box OV1, Folder 89)
- Slides, 1955-1969; Series VII
  - Related to mission work in Hong Kong, 1955-1969, n.d. (Box OV1, Folder 1-2)
  - Scenery, 1962-1963, n.d. (Box OV1, Folder 3-4)
- Addendum, 1915-1980
  - Correspondence, 1915-1980
    - Olive Anderson
      - Letters written while single missionary, 1915 Sep - 1916 Feb (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Letters written while single missionary, 1916 Sep - 1917 Nov (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Olive and Sidney Anderson to/from family in U.S.
      - While stationed in Shanghai, 1922 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - While stationed in Shanghai, 1923 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - While in New York and return to Shanghai, 1934 Feb - 1943 Oct (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - While in Shanghai, U.S., and Hong Kong, 1946 Aug - 1957 Nov (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - While in U.S., Shanghai, and Hong Kong, 1957 Nov - 1959 Dec (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - While in Hong Kong, including many letters from son, 1962 Mar - 1964 Mar (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - Following retirement, in Atlanta, GA, 1966 -1973 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - Following retirement, in Atlanta, GA, 1974-1975 Apr (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - To/from son and siblings, 1975 May- 1977 May (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - To/from son and siblings, 1977 Jul - Nov (Box 8, Folder 12)
      - To/from son and siblings, 1977 Dec-1978 Jan (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Letters of Bessie Lipscomb, Olive's mother
      - To Sidney and Olive, 1920 Dec - 1952 Jun (Box 8, Folder 14)
      - To Sidney and Olive, 1952 Jul - Dec (Box 8, Folder 15)
      - To Sidney and Olive, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 16)
      - To Sidney and Olive, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 17)
      - To Sidney and Olive, 1955-1956 (Box 8, Folder 18)
      - To Sidney and Olive, 1957 Jan - Jun (Box 8, Folder 19)
      - To Sidney and Olive, 1957 Jul - Dec (Box 9, Folder 20)
      - To Sidney and Olive, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Letters of Andersons to/from others
      - Anderson - Cummings (Box 9, Folder 22)
      - Daubs - Lois (Box 9, Folder 23)
      - Mao - Ruth (Box 9, Folder 24)
      - Saunders - Tsiang (Box 9, Folder 25)
      - U-Kyaw - Zih (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Circular letters of the Andersons
      - From Shanghai, New York, New Jersey, 1941-1951 (Box 9, Folder 27)
      - From Hong Kong and Georgia, 1952-1973 (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Letters of others
      - Beall - Saunders, including re. student refugees (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Condolences/ tributes
      - Alsup - Cox, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 30)
      - Dakis - Keating, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 31)
      - Lipscomb - Queen, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 32)
      - Rast - Wyatt, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Letters to/from Sidney Anderson, Jr.
      - Related to his parents, 1978-1980 (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - Writings, 1923-1960s
    - Writings of Sidney and Olive, including poems, 1925-1951 (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - Sermons by Sidney Anderson
      Scope and Contents
      Arranged alphabetically by title
      - Including "Building of the Nation of China"; "Christianity in China" (Box 9, Folder 36)
      - Including "Deciding Factor in Christian Missions" (Box 9, Folder 37)
      - Including "God in the Background of China" (Box 10, Folder 38)
      - Including "Good New for Everyone" (Box 10, Folder 39)
      - Including "The Motive of the Mission" (Box 10, Folder 40)
      - Including "The Power of the Holy Spirit" (Box 10, Folder 41)
      - Including "The Source of Abundant Life" (Box 10, Folder 42)
      - Including Ward Memorial Church farewell; "What Effect has Communism had on the Work of the Methodist Church in Shanghai?" (Box 10, Folder 43)
      - Including "You are God's Temple" (Box 10, Folder 44)
    - Notes of Sidney Anderson
      - Bible studies and sermon notes (Box 10, Folder 45)
    - Writings of others
      - Including pamphlet "The Three Ns - Nine naughty but nice - and how they began" (re. Chinese women who met at a YWCA English conversation class in 1939) (Box 10, Folder 46)
      - Diary of Bessie W. Lipscomb, mother of Olive, 1923-1924 (Box 10, Folder 47)
  - Documentation of Mission Work, 1921-1963
    - Shanghai and Moore Memorial Church, 1921-1950 (Box 10, Folder 48)
    - Hong Kong: Wesley Village, North Point Methodist Church; Chung Chi College, Ward Memorial Methodist Church, 1951-1963 (Box 10, Folder 49)
    - Hong Kong: Wesley Village, North Point Methodist Church; Chung Chi College, Ward Memorial Methodist Church, 1951-1963 (Box 10, Folder 50)
  - Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1951-1978
    - Biographies, clippings, memorial services (Box 10, Folder 51)
    - Financial information, wills (Box 10, Folder 52)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 11, Folder 53)
    - Regarding Bessie W. Lipscomb, mother of Olive (Box 11, Folder 54)
    - Address books, memo books (Box 11, Folder 55-56)
    - Anderson family Bible (Box 11, Folder 57)
    - News clippings re. friends, memorial programs (Box 11, Folder 58)
    - Booklets (Box 11, Folder 59)
    - Greeting cards (Box 12, Folder 60)
    - Craft items (Box 12, Folder 61)
    - Re. Wesley Woods Retirement Community (Box 12, Folder 62)
    - Chinese language material (Box 12, Folder 63)
    - China-related material (Box 12, Folder 64-65)
    - Photographs of Sidney and Olive Anderson, of other individuals (mostly Chinese), groups, buildings, weddings (Box 12, Folder 66-68)